<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#mez">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/aml-corpus/0.1.0"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/aml-corpus"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/aml-corpus/0.1.0/eng@"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/aml-corpus/eng@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/aml-corpus/0.1.0/eng@.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/aml-corpus/eng@.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication name="MEZ Stack" showAs="MEZ Stack" date="2024-01-01" number="0.1.0"/>
      <references source="#mez">
        <TLCOrganization eId="mez" href="/ontology/organization/mez" showAs="Momentum EZ"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="fmu" href="/ontology/organization/pk.fmu" showAs="Financial Monitoring Unit"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="sbp" href="/ontology/organization/pk.sbp" showAs="State Bank of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="secp" href="/ontology/organization/pk.secp" showAs="Securities and Exchange Commission of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="nacta" href="/ontology/organization/pk.nacta" showAs="National Counter Terrorism Authority"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="fatf" href="/ontology/organization/intl.fatf" showAs="Financial Action Task Force"/>
      </references>
    </meta>

    <preface>
      <p eId="preface-1">Pakistan AML/CFT legal corpus for the Momentum EZ compliance stack.
        Consolidates key provisions from the Anti-Money Laundering Act, 2010 (Act VII of 2010),
        the Anti-Terrorism Act, 1997 (Act XXVII of 1997, CFT provisions), the SECP AML/CFT
        Regulations, 2018, and the SBP AML/CFT Regulations for Banks. Thresholds and requirements
        reflect the legal position as of January 2024.</p>
    </preface>

    <body>
      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART I: ANTI-MONEY LAUNDERING ACT, 2010 (Act VII of 2010)       -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <part eId="part-amla">
        <heading>Anti-Money Laundering Act, 2010 (Act VII of 2010)</heading>

        <!-- Section 2: Definitions -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-2">
          <num>Section 2</num>
          <heading>Definitions</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-2.p1">In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject
              or context:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-2.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-2.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p><def refersTo="#financial-institution">"financial institution"</def> means a
                  banking company, a non-banking finance company, a modaraba, a leasing company,
                  an insurance company, a securities broker, a foreign exchange dealer, a money
                  service business, a payment system operator, or any other entity as the Federal
                  Government may by notification declare to be a financial institution for the
                  purposes of this Act.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-2.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p><def refersTo="#reporting-entity">"reporting entity"</def> means a financial
                  institution, a designated non-financial business or profession, or any other
                  person or entity as the Federal Government may by notification prescribe as a
                  reporting entity.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-2.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p><def refersTo="#suspicious-transaction">"suspicious transaction"</def> means a
                  transaction, whether or not made in cash, which, to a person acting in good
                  faith: (i) gives rise to a reasonable suspicion that it may involve the proceeds
                  of an offence regardless of the value of the transaction; or (ii) appears to be
                  made in circumstances of unusual or unjustified complexity; or (iii) appears to
                  have no economic rationale or lawful purpose; or (iv) gives rise to a reasonable
                  suspicion that it may involve financing of terrorism or a proscribed
                  organization.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-2.bl1.i4">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p><def refersTo="#beneficial-owner">"beneficial owner"</def> means the natural
                  person who ultimately owns or controls a customer or on whose behalf a
                  transaction or activity is being conducted, and includes any person who
                  exercises ultimate effective control over a legal person or arrangement.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-2.bl1.i5">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p><def refersTo="#dnfbp">"designated non-financial business or profession"</def>
                  means: (i) a real estate agent; (ii) a dealer in precious metals or precious
                  stones; (iii) a lawyer, notary, or other independent legal professional when
                  preparing for or carrying out transactions for a client concerning buying and
                  selling of real estate, managing client money or assets, managing bank or
                  securities accounts, or creation or management of legal persons or arrangements;
                  (iv) a trust and company service provider; (v) an accountant; or (vi) any other
                  business or profession as the Federal Government may by notification
                  prescribe.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-2.bl1.i6">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p><def refersTo="#predicate-offence">"predicate offence"</def> means any offence
                  the commission of which generates proceeds that may become the subject of an
                  offence under Section 3 of this Act, and includes offences set out in the
                  Schedule to this Act, including but not limited to fraud, forgery, corruption,
                  drug trafficking, kidnapping, extortion, smuggling, tax evasion, and any
                  offence punishable under the Anti-Terrorism Act, 1997.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 3: Money Laundering Offence -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-3">
          <num>Section 3</num>
          <heading>Offence of Money Laundering</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-3.p1">A person shall be guilty of the offence of money laundering
              if the person:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-3.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-3.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>acquires, possesses, uses, converts, or transfers property knowing or having
                  reason to believe that such property is the proceeds of a predicate offence;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-3.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>conceals or disguises the true nature, source, location, disposition, movement,
                  or ownership of property knowing or having reason to believe that such property
                  is the proceeds of a predicate offence; or</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-3.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>holds, conceals, or facilitates any dealing in property knowing or having
                  reason to believe that such property is the proceeds of a predicate offence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-3.p2">It shall not be necessary to establish a conviction for the
              predicate offence in order to prove the offence of money laundering.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-3.p3">The offence of money laundering extends to property derived
              directly or indirectly from the predicate offence, including income, profits, or
              other benefits derived from the proceeds.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 4: Punishment -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-4">
          <num>Section 4</num>
          <heading>Punishment for Money Laundering</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-4.p1">Whoever commits the offence of money laundering shall be
              punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than
              <num value="1">one year</num> but may extend to <num value="10">ten years</num>
              and shall also be liable to a fine which may extend to
              <num value="1000000">PKR 1,000,000</num> (one million rupees), or twice the value
              of the property involved in the offence, whichever is greater.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-4.p2">Where the offence of money laundering has been committed by
              a body corporate, every person who at the time the offence was committed was in
              charge of and was responsible to the body corporate for the conduct of the business
              of the body corporate, as well as the body corporate, shall be deemed to be guilty
              of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished
              accordingly.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-4.p3">Property involved in or derived from money laundering shall
              be liable to forfeiture to the Federal Government, regardless of whether any
              person has been convicted of the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 6: Customer Due Diligence -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-6">
          <num>Section 6</num>
          <heading>Customer Due Diligence</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-6.p1">Every reporting entity shall carry out customer due diligence
              (CDD) measures when:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-6.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>establishing a business relationship;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>carrying out an occasional transaction above the applicable threshold
                  (PKR 2,000,000 for cash transactions, USD 1,000 equivalent for wire
                  transfers);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>there is a suspicion of money laundering or financing of terrorism; or</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl1.i4">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the reporting entity has doubts about the veracity or adequacy of previously
                  obtained customer identification data.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-6.p2">CDD measures shall include:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-6.bl2">
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl2.i1">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p><strong>Identity verification:</strong> identifying the customer and verifying
                  the customer's identity using reliable, independent source documents, data, or
                  information. For natural persons, this shall include the customer's full name,
                  date of birth, residential address, and Computerised National Identity Card
                  (CNIC) number or passport number. For legal persons, this shall include the
                  entity's name, registration number, registered address, and details of
                  directors or partners.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl2.i2">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p><strong>Beneficial ownership:</strong> identifying the beneficial owner and
                  taking reasonable measures to verify the identity of the beneficial owner,
                  such that the reporting entity is satisfied that it knows who the beneficial
                  owner is, including for legal persons and legal arrangements, understanding
                  the ownership and control structure.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl2.i3">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p><strong>Purpose and nature:</strong> understanding and, as appropriate,
                  obtaining information on the purpose and intended nature of the business
                  relationship.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6.bl2.i4">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p><strong>Ongoing monitoring:</strong> conducting ongoing due diligence on the
                  business relationship and scrutiny of transactions undertaken throughout the
                  course of that relationship to ensure that the transactions being conducted
                  are consistent with the reporting entity's knowledge of the customer, their
                  business and risk profile, including where necessary the source of funds.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-6.p3">A reporting entity shall apply a risk-based approach to CDD.
              Where the risk of money laundering or terrorist financing is higher, enhanced
              measures shall be taken; where the risk is lower, simplified measures may be
              permitted, subject to conditions prescribed by the relevant supervisory authority.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 6A: Enhanced Due Diligence -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-6a">
          <num>Section 6A</num>
          <heading>Enhanced Due Diligence for Politically Exposed Persons and High-Risk Countries</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-6a.p1">Every reporting entity shall apply enhanced due diligence
              (EDD) measures, in addition to the CDD measures required under Section 6, in the
              following circumstances:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-6a.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-6a.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p><strong>Politically Exposed Persons (PEPs):</strong> where the customer or
                  the beneficial owner is a PEP, whether domestic or foreign, the reporting
                  entity shall: (i) obtain senior management approval before establishing or
                  continuing the business relationship; (ii) take reasonable measures to
                  establish the source of wealth and source of funds; and (iii) conduct enhanced
                  ongoing monitoring of the business relationship.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6a.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p><strong>High-risk countries:</strong> where the customer, beneficial owner, or
                  transaction involves a country identified by the FATF as high-risk or under
                  increased monitoring (grey list or black list), the reporting entity shall
                  apply counter-measures proportionate to the risks, which may include: enhanced
                  scrutiny of the business relationship; requiring additional documentation on
                  the source and purpose of funds; and reporting the relationship or transaction
                  to the FMU.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-6a.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p><strong>Correspondent banking:</strong> for cross-border correspondent banking
                  relationships, the reporting entity shall: gather sufficient information about
                  the respondent institution to understand the nature of its business; determine
                  from publicly available information the reputation of the institution and the
                  quality of supervision; assess the respondent institution's AML/CFT controls;
                  and obtain senior management approval before establishing new correspondent
                  relationships.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 7: Suspicious Transaction Reporting -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-7">
          <num>Section 7</num>
          <heading>Suspicious Transaction Reports</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7.p1">Where a reporting entity has reasonable grounds to suspect
              that a transaction, attempted transaction, or funds are the proceeds of an offence
              or are related to or to be used for financing of terrorism, the reporting entity
              shall as soon as possible but not later than <num value="7">seven</num> working
              days submit a suspicious transaction report (STR) to the Financial Monitoring
              Unit (FMU).</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7.p2">The STR shall contain such particulars as the FMU may
              prescribe, including but not limited to: the identity of the persons involved;
              the nature and details of the transaction; the grounds for suspicion; and any
              other information that may assist the FMU in its analysis.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7.p3">STRs shall be filed through the goAML portal maintained by
              the FMU, or through such other electronic means as the FMU may prescribe.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7.p4">The obligation to submit an STR applies regardless of the
              amount of the transaction and regardless of whether the transaction was completed
              or attempted.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 7A: Currency Transaction Reports -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-7a">
          <num>Section 7A</num>
          <heading>Currency Transaction Reports</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7a.p1">Every reporting entity shall submit a currency transaction
              report (CTR) to the FMU in respect of every cash transaction exceeding
              <num value="2000000">PKR 2,000,000</num> (two million rupees) or its equivalent
              in foreign currency, whether the transaction is conducted as a single transaction
              or as several transactions that appear to be linked.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7a.p2">CTRs shall be submitted within <num value="15">fifteen</num>
              days of the end of the calendar month in which the transaction was conducted,
              through the goAML portal or such other means as the FMU may prescribe.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7a.p3">Where a reporting entity suspects that a transaction has been
              structured (i.e., deliberately split into amounts below the CTR threshold to avoid
              reporting), the reporting entity shall also file an STR under Section 7.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 7B: Cross-Border Wire Transfer Requirements -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-7b">
          <num>Section 7B</num>
          <heading>Cross-Border Wire Transfer Requirements</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7b.p1">Every financial institution ordering a cross-border wire
              transfer shall ensure that the wire transfer is accompanied by the following
              originator information:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-7b.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-7b.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name of the originator;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-7b.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the originator's account number or, in the absence of an account, a unique
                  transaction reference number;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-7b.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the originator's address, CNIC number, customer identification number,
                  or date and place of birth.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7b.p2">For wire transfers exceeding <num value="1000">USD 1,000</num>
              or its equivalent in other currencies, the ordering financial institution shall
              verify the identity of the originator prior to execution of the transfer and
              include the following beneficiary information:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-7b.bl2">
              <item eId="sec-amla-7b.bl2.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name of the beneficiary; and</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-7b.bl2.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the beneficiary's account number or, in the absence of an account, a unique
                  transaction reference number.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7b.p3">The requirements of this section shall be applied in
              compliance with FATF Recommendation 16 and are applicable to wire transfers
              using SWIFT MT103 messages, ISO 20022 pacs.008 messages, or any other payment
              messaging standard.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-7b.p4">Intermediary financial institutions in a payment chain shall
              ensure that all originator and beneficiary information accompanying a wire transfer
              is retained with the transfer. Failure to include required originator or beneficiary
              information shall constitute grounds for rejection or suspension of the transfer.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 8: Record Keeping -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-8">
          <num>Section 8</num>
          <heading>Record Keeping</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-8.p1">Every reporting entity shall maintain the following records
              for a period of not less than <num value="5">five years</num> from the date of
              completion of the transaction or from the date of termination of the business
              relationship, whichever is later:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-8.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-8.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all records obtained through CDD measures, including copies of identification
                  documents, account files, and business correspondence;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-8.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all transaction records, including details sufficient to reconstruct individual
                  transactions so as to provide, if necessary, evidence for prosecution of
                  criminal activity; and</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-8.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all internal reports, risk assessments, and analysis related to STRs and CTRs.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-8.p2">Records may be maintained in electronic form provided the
              reporting entity can produce legible hard copies upon request by the FMU, a
              supervisory authority, or a law enforcement agency within a reasonable time.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-8.p3">The FMU or the relevant supervisory authority may, by order,
              require a reporting entity to retain specified records for a period longer than
              <num value="5">five years</num> in connection with an ongoing investigation or
              proceeding.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Section 13: Tipping-Off Prohibition -->
        <section eId="sec-amla-13">
          <num>Section 13</num>
          <heading>Prohibition on Tipping Off</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-amla-13.p1">No reporting entity, and no director, officer, employee, or
              agent of a reporting entity, shall disclose to any person the fact that:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-amla-13.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-amla-13.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an STR or related information has been or is being filed with the FMU;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-13.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an investigation into money laundering or financing of terrorism is being or
                  may be conducted; or</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-amla-13.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any order for freezing, seizure, or forfeiture of property has been made or
                  is being sought under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-amla-13.p2">Any person who contravenes this section shall be guilty of
              an offence and shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend
              to <num value="3">three years</num> and shall also be liable to a fine which may
              extend to <num value="500000">PKR 500,000</num>.</p>
            <p eId="sec-amla-13.p3">This section does not apply to disclosure: (a) between
              financial institutions within the same group for AML/CFT compliance purposes;
              (b) between a reporting entity and its legal adviser in connection with seeking
              legal advice; or (c) between competent authorities in the performance of their
              functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART II: SECP AML/CFT REGULATIONS, 2018                         -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <part eId="part-secp">
        <heading>SECP AML/CFT Regulations, 2018</heading>

        <!-- Regulation 3: Risk-Based Approach -->
        <section eId="sec-secp-3">
          <num>Regulation 3</num>
          <heading>Risk-Based Approach</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-secp-3.p1">Every regulated person shall adopt a risk-based approach to
              combating money laundering and financing of terrorism. This shall include:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-secp-3.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-secp-3.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>conducting a comprehensive risk assessment of its business, taking into
                  account risk factors relating to customers, countries or geographic areas,
                  products and services, transactions, and delivery channels;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-3.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>documenting the risk assessment and making it available to the SECP upon
                  request;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-3.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>classifying customers into risk categories (low, medium, and high) based on
                  the risk assessment; and</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-3.bl1.i4">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>applying CDD measures commensurate with the identified risk level, with
                  enhanced measures for higher-risk relationships and simplified measures
                  permitted for lower-risk relationships.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-secp-3.p2">The risk assessment shall be updated at least annually, or
              more frequently in the event of a material change in the regulated person's business
              or risk profile, or in the event of a new emerging risk identified by the SECP,
              FATF, or FMU.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Regulation 5: CDD Measures -->
        <section eId="sec-secp-5">
          <num>Regulation 5</num>
          <heading>Customer Due Diligence Measures</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-secp-5.p1">CDD measures to be applied by regulated persons shall be
              proportionate to the risk associated with the customer relationship:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-secp-5.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-secp-5.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p><strong>Simplified CDD (low risk):</strong> for customers assessed as low
                  risk, the regulated person may verify the identity of the customer and
                  beneficial owner after the establishment of the business relationship,
                  provided that: the risk of money laundering has been effectively managed;
                  verification is completed within <num value="30">30</num> days of account
                  opening; and the regulated person has adopted procedures to limit the
                  number and types of transactions that can be performed prior to
                  verification.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-5.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p><strong>Standard CDD (medium risk):</strong> for customers assessed as medium
                  risk, verification of identity shall be completed before or at the time of
                  establishing the business relationship. Source of funds documentation shall
                  be obtained where the transaction exceeds
                  <num value="5000000">PKR 5,000,000</num>.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-5.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p><strong>Enhanced CDD (high risk):</strong> for customers assessed as high
                  risk, including PEPs, customers from FATF grey-list or black-list
                  jurisdictions, and complex or unusual transactions, the regulated person
                  shall: obtain senior management approval; establish the source of wealth and
                  source of funds through documentary evidence; and apply enhanced ongoing
                  monitoring with transaction review at least monthly.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Regulation 7: Ongoing Monitoring -->
        <section eId="sec-secp-7">
          <num>Regulation 7</num>
          <heading>Ongoing Monitoring</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-secp-7.p1">Every regulated person shall conduct ongoing monitoring of
              all business relationships and transactions to ensure that they are consistent with
              the regulated person's knowledge of the customer and the customer's business and
              risk profile.</p>
            <p eId="sec-secp-7.p2">The frequency of monitoring reviews shall be commensurate
              with the customer's risk classification:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-secp-7.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-secp-7.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Low-risk customers: annual review of the business relationship and
                  transaction patterns.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-7.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Medium-risk customers: quarterly review of transaction patterns and
                  periodic re-verification of customer information.</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-7.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>High-risk customers: monthly review of all transactions; automated
                  transaction monitoring alerts where available; and senior management review
                  of the relationship at least every <num value="6">six</num> months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-secp-7.p3">Where ongoing monitoring reveals unusual or suspicious
              activity, the regulated person shall conduct further analysis and, where the
              suspicion is confirmed, file an STR with the FMU within the prescribed timeframe.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Regulation 8: STR Obligations -->
        <section eId="sec-secp-8">
          <num>Regulation 8</num>
          <heading>Suspicious Transaction Report Obligations</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-secp-8.p1">Every regulated person shall file STRs with the FMU within
              <num value="7">seven</num> working days of forming a suspicion, through the
              goAML portal. The compliance officer shall be responsible for the decision to file
              and the quality of information contained in the STR.</p>
            <p eId="sec-secp-8.p2">The STR shall include, at a minimum: the identity of the
              persons involved; account details and transaction history relevant to the
              suspicion; the nature and date of the suspicious activity; the reason for
              suspicion; and any supporting documents or information.</p>
            <p eId="sec-secp-8.p3">Where the regulated person identifies a transaction that
              may relate to the financing of terrorism or a proscribed organization, the STR
              shall be filed immediately and the regulated person shall not proceed with the
              transaction until authorized by the FMU.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Regulation 9: Compliance Officer -->
        <section eId="sec-secp-9">
          <num>Regulation 9</num>
          <heading>Compliance Officer Appointment</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-secp-9.p1">Every regulated person shall appoint a compliance officer
              at a sufficiently senior level, with the following requirements:</p>
            <blockList eId="sec-secp-9.bl1">
              <item eId="sec-secp-9.bl1.i1">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the appointment shall be approved by the board of directors or equivalent
                  senior management body;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-9.bl1.i2">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the compliance officer shall have direct access to the board and to the
                  regulated person's customer records and transaction information;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-9.bl1.i3">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the compliance officer shall have completed FATF-aligned AML/CFT training
                  and shall undergo refresher training at least annually; and</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sec-secp-9.bl1.i4">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the compliance officer shall be responsible for ensuring the regulated
                  person's compliance with the Act, these Regulations, and any directions
                  issued by the SECP or the FMU.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="sec-secp-9.p2">The name and contact details of the compliance officer shall
              be communicated to the SECP and the FMU within <num value="30">30</num> days of
              appointment or any change in appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <!-- Regulation 12: Record Retention -->
        <section eId="sec-secp-12">
          <num>Regulation 12</num>
          <heading>Record Retention</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-secp-12.p1">Every regulated person shall retain all CDD records,
              transaction records, internal analysis, and STR-related records for a minimum of
              <num value="5">five years</num> from the date of the transaction or from the date
              of termination of the business relationship, whichever is later.</p>
            <p eId="sec-secp-12.p2">Records must be sufficient to permit reconstruction of
              individual transactions, including the amounts and types of currencies involved,
              and must be available to the SECP, the FMU, and law enforcement authorities upon
              request without undue delay.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART III: SBP AML/CFT REGULATIONS (Key Thresholds)              -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <part eId="part-sbp">
        <heading>SBP AML/CFT Regulations for Banks -- Key Thresholds and Requirements</heading>

        <section eId="sec-sbp-ctr">
          <num>SBP-CTR</num>
          <heading>Currency Transaction Report Threshold</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-ctr.p1">Every bank and financial institution supervised by the State
              Bank of Pakistan shall file a CTR with the FMU for every cash transaction
              (deposit, withdrawal, currency exchange, or transfer) exceeding
              <num value="2000000">PKR 2,000,000</num> (two million rupees) or its equivalent
              in foreign currency, whether conducted as a single transaction or as multiple
              transactions that appear to be linked or structured.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sec-sbp-wire">
          <num>SBP-WIRE</num>
          <heading>Wire Transfer Originator Information Threshold</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-wire.p1">For cross-border wire transfers, full originator information
              (name, account number, address or national identity number, and date and place of
              birth) is required for all transfers exceeding
              <num value="1000">USD 1,000</num> or its equivalent in other currencies, in
              accordance with FATF Recommendation 16.</p>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-wire.p2">For wire transfers of <num value="1000">USD 1,000</num>
              or below, the ordering institution shall include the originator's name and account
              number (or unique transaction reference). The beneficiary institution shall have
              effective risk-based procedures for identifying wire transfers that lack required
              originator information.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sec-sbp-pep">
          <num>SBP-PEP</num>
          <heading>PEP Enhanced Monitoring Duration</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-pep.p1">Enhanced monitoring of a customer identified as a Politically
              Exposed Person (PEP) shall continue for the entire duration of the business
              relationship, regardless of changes in the customer's political status. A former
              PEP shall continue to be subject to enhanced monitoring for a period determined by
              the bank's risk assessment, which shall be not less than
              <num value="12">twelve months</num> after the person ceases to hold the relevant
              position, and indefinitely where the residual risk remains elevated.</p>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-pep.p2">Banks shall screen all existing customers against updated
              PEP lists (domestic and international) at least quarterly, or upon notification
              by the FMU or SBP of additions to the lists.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sec-sbp-str">
          <num>SBP-STR</num>
          <heading>STR Filing Requirements for Banks</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-str.p1">Banks shall file STRs with the FMU within
              <num value="7">seven</num> working days of forming a suspicion, through the
              goAML portal maintained by the FMU. The STR shall be prepared by the branch
              compliance officer and reviewed and approved by the head office compliance
              function before submission.</p>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-str.p2">Where the suspicion relates to financing of terrorism, the
              bank shall file the STR immediately and shall freeze the relevant account or
              transaction pending instruction from the FMU, in accordance with the provisions
              of the Anti-Terrorism Act, 1997 and any freezing orders issued under United
              Nations Security Council Resolutions.</p>
            <p eId="sec-sbp-str.p3">Banks shall maintain internal records of all STRs filed,
              including the outcome of the FMU's analysis where communicated, for a minimum
              of <num value="5">five years</num>.</p>
          </content>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
