<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#mez">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/financial-corpus/0.1.0"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/financial-corpus"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="pk"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/financial-corpus/0.1.0/eng@"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/financial-corpus/eng@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/financial-corpus/0.1.0/eng@.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/financial-corpus/eng@.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#mez">
        <TLCOrganization eId="sbp" href="/ontology/organization/pk.sbp" showAs="State Bank of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="secp" href="/ontology/organization/pk.secp" showAs="Securities and Exchange Commission of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="mez" href="/ontology/organization/momentum-ez" showAs="Momentum EZ"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="natl_assembly" href="/ontology/organization/pk.national-assembly" showAs="National Assembly of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="nadra" href="/ontology/organization/pk.nadra" showAs="National Database and Registration Authority"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="fmu" href="/ontology/organization/pk.fmu" showAs="Financial Monitoring Unit"/>
      </references>
      <publication name="MEZ Stack" showAs="MEZ Stack" date="2024-01-01" number="0.1.0"/>
    </meta>

    <preface>
      <p eId="pre_1">Pakistan financial and banking legal corpus — a machine-readable consolidation of key
        provisions from the Banking Companies Ordinance 1962, the Microfinance Institutions Ordinance
        2001, the State Bank of Pakistan Act 1956, the Payment Systems and Electronic Fund Transfers
        Act 2007, SBP Raast Regulations 2021, SBP Regulations for Electronic Money Institutions 2019,
        and the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act 1947.</p>
      <p eId="pre_2">This corpus is provided for compliance-tensor evaluation within the Momentum EZ
        stack. It does not replace the authoritative gazette text. All monetary thresholds reflect
        the position as of 1 January 2024 unless otherwise noted.</p>
    </preface>

    <body>

      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <!-- PART I — BANKING COMPANIES ORDINANCE 1962 (Ordinance LVII of 1962) -->
      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <part eId="part_bco">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Banking Companies Ordinance, 1962 (Ordinance LVII of 1962)</heading>

        <section eId="part_bco__sec_13">
          <num>13</num>
          <heading>Minimum paid-up capital</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_13__p_1">No banking company shall carry on banking business in
              Pakistan unless it has a minimum paid-up capital (net of losses) as prescribed by the
              State Bank from time to time.</p>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_13__p_2">As per SBP BSD Circular of 2022, the Minimum Capital
              Requirement (MCR) for scheduled commercial banks is:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_bco__sec_13__list_1">
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_13__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>For all scheduled commercial banks (conventional and Islamic): paid-up capital
                  (free of losses) of not less than <num id="bco_13_mcr">PKR 10,000,000,000</num>
                  (ten billion Pakistani Rupees).</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_13__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Foreign bank branches: minimum assigned capital of
                  <num id="bco_13_foreign">USD 300,000,000</num> (three hundred million United States
                  Dollars) or equivalent, maintained as head office capital assigned to the Pakistan
                  branch.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_13__p_3">The State Bank may, by notification in the official
              gazette, revise the minimum capital requirement. Any banking company failing to meet
              the MCR shall be subject to restrictions on dividend distribution, branch expansion,
              and new business lines, and may have its licence suspended or cancelled under
              section 14.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_bco__sec_14">
          <num>14</num>
          <heading>Cash reserve requirement (CRR)</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_14__p_1">Every banking company shall maintain with the State Bank
              a cash reserve computed as a percentage of its time and demand liabilities in
              Pakistan.</p>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_14__p_2">The current Cash Reserve Requirement is
              <num id="bco_14_crr_rate">5%</num> of total demand and time liabilities (DTL), to be
              maintained on a daily average basis over a bi-weekly period.</p>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_14__p_3">Demand liabilities include current deposits, demand
              portions of savings deposits, margins held against letters of credit or guarantees,
              and any other liability payable on demand. Time liabilities include fixed deposits,
              time portions of savings deposits, borrowings from other institutions, and any other
              liability payable after a notice period or at a fixed date.</p>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_14__p_4">Failure to maintain the required CRR on any day of the
              maintenance period shall attract a penalty at a rate equal to three percentage points
              above the prevailing SBP policy rate, applied to the shortfall amount on a daily
              basis.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_bco__sec_22">
          <num>22</num>
          <heading>Statutory liquidity requirement (SLR)</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_22__p_1">In addition to the CRR under section 14, every banking
              company shall maintain liquid assets as a percentage of its time and demand
              liabilities.</p>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_22__p_2">The Statutory Liquidity Requirement currently stands at a
              minimum of <num id="bco_22_slr_rate">18%</num> of time and demand liabilities, to be
              maintained in the form of:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1">
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cash in excess of CRR;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>gold valued at a price not exceeding the current market price;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Government of Pakistan Market Treasury Bills (MTBs);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Pakistan Investment Bonds (PIBs);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>Ijara Sukuk issued by the Government of Pakistan;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_22__list_1__item_f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other approved security as notified by SBP from time to time.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_22__p_3">Penalties for SLR shortfall are computed on the same
              basis as CRR shortfall penalties under section 14.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_bco__sec_27">
          <num>27</num>
          <heading>Restrictions on loans to directors and related parties</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_27__p_1">No banking company shall:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_bco__sec_27__list_1">
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_27__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>grant any loan or advance on the security of its own shares;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_27__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>grant unsecured loans or advances to any of its directors, or to any firm or
                  company in which any of its directors is interested as partner, director, or
                  guarantor, or to any individual in respect of whom any of its directors is a
                  guarantor;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_27__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>grant to any single person or group of persons aggregate loans, advances, or
                  credit facilities exceeding <num id="bco_27_single_limit">30%</num> of the
                  bank's equity as per SBP Prudential Regulations (single borrower exposure
                  limit);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_27__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>grant to any group of connected persons aggregate exposure exceeding
                  <num id="bco_27_group_limit">50%</num> of the bank's equity (group exposure
                  limit).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_27__p_2">Any loan or advance made in contravention of this
              section shall be recoverable forthwith, and the directors who sanctioned such loan
              shall be jointly and severally liable to the banking company for any loss arising
              therefrom.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_bco__sec_29">
          <num>29</num>
          <heading>Capital adequacy ratio</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_29__p_1">Every banking company shall maintain a capital adequacy
              ratio (CAR) in accordance with the Basel III framework as implemented by SBP through
              its Prudential Regulations and circulars.</p>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_29__p_2">The minimum capital adequacy requirements are:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_bco__sec_29__list_1">
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_29__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Minimum total Capital Adequacy Ratio (CAR):
                  <num id="bco_29_total_car">11.5%</num> of risk-weighted assets, inclusive of the
                  capital conservation buffer of 2.5%;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_29__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Minimum Common Equity Tier 1 (CET-1) ratio:
                  <num id="bco_29_cet1">6.0%</num> of risk-weighted assets;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_29__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Minimum Tier 1 capital ratio: <num id="bco_29_tier1">7.5%</num> of
                  risk-weighted assets;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_29__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Domestically Systemically Important Banks (D-SIBs) shall maintain an additional
                  Higher Loss Absorbency (HLA) surcharge of up to
                  <num id="bco_29_dsib">2.0%</num> of risk-weighted assets, as determined by SBP
                  based on systemic importance assessment.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_29__p_3">Risk-weighted assets shall be computed using the
              Standardized Approach for credit risk, the Basic Indicator Approach or Standardized
              Approach for operational risk, and the Standardized Measurement Method for market
              risk, as prescribed by SBP.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_bco__sec_33">
          <num>33</num>
          <heading>Powers of SBP to issue directives, inspect, and penalize</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_33__p_1">The State Bank may, by order in writing:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_bco__sec_33__list_1">
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_33__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>issue directives to any banking company to take such action as the State Bank
                  considers necessary in the interests of depositors, the banking company, or the
                  banking system as a whole;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_33__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>cause an inspection to be made by one or more of its officers of any banking
                  company and its books and accounts, and the banking company shall produce before
                  the inspecting officer all such books, accounts, and other documents in its
                  custody or power as may be required;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_33__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>impose monetary penalties on a banking company for failure to comply with any
                  direction, regulation, or provision of this Ordinance, subject to a maximum
                  penalty of <num id="bco_33_max_penalty">PKR 250,000,000</num> (two hundred and
                  fifty million Pakistani Rupees) per contravention or such higher amount as may
                  be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_33__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>remove from office any director, chief executive, or officer of a banking
                  company who is found to be not fit and proper, or who has acted in a manner
                  prejudicial to the interests of the banking company or its depositors;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_bco__sec_33__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>require a banking company to convene a meeting of its board of directors to
                  consider such matters as the State Bank may direct.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_bco__sec_33__p_2">The State Bank shall, before imposing any penalty or
              removing any person under this section, give the banking company or person concerned
              a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <!-- PART II — MICROFINANCE INSTITUTIONS ORDINANCE 2001                  -->
      <!--          (Ordinance LI of 2001)                                     -->
      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <part eId="part_mfi">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Microfinance Institutions Ordinance, 2001 (Ordinance LI of 2001)</heading>

        <section eId="part_mfi__sec_3">
          <num>3</num>
          <heading>Licensing by SBP required for all microfinance banks</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_3__p_1">No company shall carry on the business of a microfinance
              bank in Pakistan except under and in accordance with a licence issued by the State
              Bank of Pakistan under this Ordinance.</p>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_3__p_2">An application for a microfinance banking licence shall
              be accompanied by:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_mfi__sec_3__list_1">
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_3__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>evidence of paid-up capital meeting the minimum prescribed under section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_3__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a certified copy of the memorandum and articles of association;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_3__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>particulars of directors and chief executive, with fit and proper declarations
                  as prescribed by SBP;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_3__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a five-year business plan demonstrating the viability of the proposed
                  microfinance operations and projected outreach;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_3__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>details of the proposed AML/CFT compliance framework and internal audit
                  arrangements.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_3__p_3">The State Bank may refuse to grant a licence if it is not
              satisfied that the applicant has adequate capital, management capability, or
              compliance infrastructure to operate as a microfinance bank.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_mfi__sec_6">
          <num>6</num>
          <heading>Minimum paid-up capital for microfinance banks</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_6__p_1">The minimum paid-up capital (free of losses) for
              microfinance banks (MFBs), as revised by SBP circular of 2023:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_mfi__sec_6__list_1">
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_6__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Nationwide microfinance bank (operating in more than one province or federal
                  territory): <num id="mfi_6_nationwide">PKR 1,000,000,000</num> (one billion
                  Pakistani Rupees);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_6__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Province-wide microfinance bank (operating within a single province):
                  <num id="mfi_6_province">PKR 500,000,000</num> (five hundred million Pakistani
                  Rupees);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_6__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>District-level microfinance bank (operating within a single district or
                  designated area): <num id="mfi_6_district">PKR 300,000,000</num> (three hundred
                  million Pakistani Rupees).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_mfi__sec_9">
          <num>9</num>
          <heading>Maximum individual loan exposure</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_9__p_1">Microfinance banks shall observe the following lending
              limits as prescribed by SBP Prudential Regulations for Microfinance Banks:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_mfi__sec_9__list_1">
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_9__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>General micro credit: maximum loan size
                  <num id="mfi_9_micro">PKR 500,000</num> (five hundred thousand Pakistani
                  Rupees) per individual borrower;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_9__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Micro enterprise loan: maximum loan size
                  <num id="mfi_9_enterprise">PKR 3,000,000</num> (three million Pakistani
                  Rupees) per borrower;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_9__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Housing microfinance: maximum loan size
                  <num id="mfi_9_housing">PKR 3,000,000</num> (three million Pakistani Rupees)
                  per borrower;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_9__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Group lending: maximum loan per group member
                  <num id="mfi_9_group">PKR 500,000</num> (five hundred thousand Pakistani
                  Rupees).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_9__p_2">The aggregate exposure of an MFB to any single borrower
              or group of connected borrowers shall not exceed <num id="mfi_9_agg">10%</num> of
              the bank's equity.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_mfi__sec_14">
          <num>14</num>
          <heading>Deposit protection fund participation</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_14__p_1">Every microfinance bank licensed under this Ordinance
              shall participate in the Deposit Protection Corporation (DPC) established by SBP
              for the protection of depositors.</p>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_14__p_2">MFB deposits are insured by the DPC up to a coverage
              limit of <num id="mfi_14_dpc">PKR 500,000</num> (five hundred thousand Pakistani
              Rupees) per depositor per bank, as notified by SBP.</p>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_14__p_3">Each MFB shall pay annual premiums to the DPC at the
              rate prescribed by SBP, computed as a percentage of the bank's assessed deposit
              base. The premium rate shall not exceed <num id="mfi_14_premium">0.16%</num> of
              assessed deposits per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_mfi__sec_18">
          <num>18</num>
          <heading>SBP supervision and examination powers</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_18__p_1">The State Bank may, at any time, cause an inspection
              to be made by one or more of its officers of any microfinance bank and its books,
              accounts, and records.</p>
            <p eId="part_mfi__sec_18__p_2">The State Bank may:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_mfi__sec_18__list_1">
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_18__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>require the production of books, accounts, and documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_18__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>examine on oath any director, officer, or employee of the microfinance bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_18__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>issue directives requiring the microfinance bank to take corrective action
                  within a specified time;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_mfi__sec_18__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>impose penalties, suspend or cancel the licence, or require the microfinance
                  bank to submit a recapitalization plan if capital falls below the prescribed
                  minimum.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <!-- PART III — PAYMENT SYSTEMS AND EFT ACT 2007 (Act V of 2007) +      -->
      <!--            SBP RAAST REGULATIONS 2021                               -->
      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <part eId="part_ps">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Payment Systems and Electronic Fund Transfers Act, 2007 (Act V of 2007) and
          SBP Raast Regulations, 2021</heading>

        <section eId="part_ps__sec_3">
          <num>3</num>
          <heading>SBP authorization required for payment system operators</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__sec_3__p_1">No person shall operate, or hold himself out as
              operating, a designated payment system except under and in accordance with an
              authorization granted by the State Bank under this Act.</p>
            <p eId="part_ps__sec_3__p_2">An application for authorization shall contain:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_ps__sec_3__list_1">
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_3__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name, registered address, and legal form of the applicant;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_3__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a description of the payment system, its rules, and operating procedures;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_3__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>evidence of minimum net worth as prescribed by SBP (currently
                  <num id="ps_3_networth">PKR 200,000,000</num> for payment system operators);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_3__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the proposed risk management framework, including settlement risk and
                  operational risk controls;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_3__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the applicant's AML/CFT compliance program.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_ps__sec_7">
          <num>7</num>
          <heading>Settlement finality</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__sec_7__p_1">A transfer order or netting that has been effected
              through a designated payment system shall be final and irrevocable upon settlement,
              and shall not be reversed, revoked, or set aside by any court, tribunal, or
              authority.</p>
            <p eId="part_ps__sec_7__p_2">Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for
              the time being in force, including the insolvency or winding up of a participant:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_ps__sec_7__list_1">
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_7__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a transfer order entered into a designated payment system prior to the
                  commencement of insolvency proceedings shall not be affected by such
                  proceedings;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_7__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the designated payment system shall be entitled to net any obligations of the
                  insolvent participant against funds or securities held by or due to such
                  participant;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__sec_7__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>settlement made through the Pakistan Real-time Interbank Settlement Mechanism
                  (PRISM) or Raast shall be considered final upon confirmation by SBP.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_ps__raast_3">
          <num>Raast R.3</num>
          <heading>Real-time settlement through SBP Raast infrastructure</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_3__p_1">Raast is Pakistan's instant payment system developed
              and operated by the State Bank of Pakistan, providing real-time settlement of
              person-to-person (P2P), person-to-merchant (P2M), and bulk payment transactions.</p>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_3__p_2">All Raast transactions are settled in real-time through
              the SBP Raast infrastructure, with immediate and irrevocable credit to the
              beneficiary's account. Settlement finality is achieved at the moment of credit
              posting by the beneficiary institution.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_ps__raast_5">
          <num>Raast R.5</num>
          <heading>P2P transfer limits</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_5__p_1">Person-to-person (P2P) transfers through Raast are
              subject to the following limits (updated 2024):</p>
            <blockList eId="part_ps__raast_5__list_1">
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_5__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Maximum per-transaction amount:
                  <num id="raast_5_per_txn">PKR 50,000</num> (fifty thousand Pakistani
                  Rupees);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_5__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Maximum daily aggregate amount:
                  <num id="raast_5_daily">PKR 200,000</num> (two hundred thousand Pakistani
                  Rupees);</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_5__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>All P2P transfers require the sender to be authenticated via the sending
                  institution's mobile or internet banking application.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_ps__raast_6">
          <num>Raast R.6</num>
          <heading>P2M transfers and merchant onboarding</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_6__p_1">Person-to-merchant (P2M) transfers through Raast are
              not subject to a regulatory per-transaction maximum. However, the acquiring
              institution shall apply its own risk-based limits as part of its merchant risk
              management framework.</p>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_6__p_2">Merchant onboarding requirements:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_ps__raast_6__list_1">
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_6__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The acquiring institution shall complete full KYC on each merchant, including
                  verification of National Tax Number (NTN) or Computerized National Identity
                  Card (CNIC), business registration certificate, and physical or virtual
                  business address;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_6__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The acquiring institution shall assign a merchant category code (MCC) to each
                  merchant in accordance with ISO 18245;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_6__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Ongoing transaction monitoring shall be performed by the acquiring institution
                  to detect suspicious patterns, with reporting to the Financial Monitoring Unit
                  (FMU) as required under the Anti-Money Laundering Act, 2010.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_ps__raast_9">
          <num>Raast R.9</num>
          <heading>IPS participation criteria</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_9__p_1">Participation in the Raast Instant Payment System (IPS)
              is restricted to:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_ps__raast_9__list_1">
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_9__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>scheduled commercial banks licensed by SBP under the Banking Companies
                  Ordinance, 1962;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_9__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>microfinance banks licensed by SBP under the Microfinance Institutions
                  Ordinance, 2001;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_9__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Electronic Money Institutions (EMIs) licensed by SBP under the EMI
                  Regulations, 2019;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_9__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Government entities designated by SBP for bulk disbursement purposes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_9__p_2">Each participant must execute the Raast Participation
              Agreement, meet technical integration requirements, and pass SBP certification
              testing before going live on the Raast network.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_ps__raast_12">
          <num>Raast R.12</num>
          <heading>ISO 20022 message format requirement</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_12__p_1">All Raast transactions shall use the ISO 20022
              message format. The following message types are mandatory:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_ps__raast_12__list_1">
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_12__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p><num id="raast_12_pacs008">pacs.008</num> — FIToFICustomerCreditTransfer:
                  used for all payment initiation messages from the debtor institution to the
                  creditor institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_12__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p><num id="raast_12_pacs002">pacs.002</num> —
                  FIToFIPaymentStatusReport: used for all payment status responses from the
                  creditor institution to the debtor institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_12__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>pain.013 — CreditorPaymentActivationRequest: used for request-to-pay
                  messages in P2M use cases;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_ps__raast_12__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>camt.053 — BankToCustomerStatement: used for reconciliation and account
                  reporting purposes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_ps__raast_12__p_2">All participants shall conform to the Raast ISO 20022
              Message Implementation Guide published by SBP. Non-conforming messages shall be
              rejected by the Raast clearing and settlement infrastructure.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <!-- PART IV — EMI REGULATIONS 2019 (SBP)                               -->
      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <part eId="part_emi">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>SBP Regulations for Electronic Money Institutions, 2019</heading>

        <section eId="part_emi__reg_3">
          <num>R.3</num>
          <heading>SBP licensing required for EMIs</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_3__p_1">No entity shall issue electronic money, operate
              e-money wallets, or provide e-money services in Pakistan except under and in
              accordance with a licence granted by the State Bank of Pakistan under these
              Regulations.</p>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_3__p_2">An EMI licence may be granted as:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_emi__reg_3__list_1">
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_3__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Full EMI licence: authorizing the issuance of e-money, operation of e-money
                  wallets, cash-in and cash-out services through agents, and inter-wallet and
                  bank-to-wallet transfers;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_3__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Restricted EMI licence: limited to specific e-money services as determined
                  by SBP on a case-by-case basis.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_emi__reg_5">
          <num>R.5</num>
          <heading>Minimum paid-up capital</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_5__p_1">An entity applying for a full EMI licence shall
              maintain a minimum paid-up capital of
              <num id="emi_5_capital">PKR 200,000,000</num> (two hundred million Pakistani
              Rupees), free of losses, at all times.</p>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_5__p_2">The minimum paid-up capital for a restricted EMI
              licence shall be determined by SBP based on the scope of authorized services,
              but shall not be less than <num id="emi_5_restricted">PKR 50,000,000</num>
              (fifty million Pakistani Rupees).</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_emi__reg_7">
          <num>R.7</num>
          <heading>E-money wallet limits</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_7__p_1">EMI wallets are tiered based on KYC level. The
              following limits apply:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_emi__reg_7__list_1">
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_7__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Level 0 (minimum KYC — CNIC only): maximum single transaction
                  <num id="emi_7_l0_txn">PKR 25,000</num>; monthly aggregate outflow
                  <num id="emi_7_l0_monthly">PKR 200,000</num>; maximum wallet balance
                  <num id="emi_7_l0_balance">PKR 200,000</num>;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_7__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Level 1 (biometric verification via NADRA): maximum single transaction
                  <num id="emi_7_l1_txn">PKR 50,000</num>; monthly aggregate outflow
                  <num id="emi_7_l1_monthly">PKR 400,000</num>; maximum wallet balance
                  <num id="emi_7_l1_balance">PKR 400,000</num>;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_7__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Level 2 (full CDD — enhanced due diligence): maximum wallet balance
                  <num id="emi_7_l2_balance">PKR 500,000</num> (five hundred thousand
                  Pakistani Rupees); monthly throughput
                  <num id="emi_7_l2_monthly">PKR 1,000,000</num> (one million Pakistani
                  Rupees).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_7__p_2">All EMI accounts must be linked to a valid
              Computerized National Identity Card (CNIC) issued by the National Database and
              Registration Authority (NADRA). For Level 1 and above, biometric verification
              against the NADRA database is mandatory at the time of account opening.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_emi__reg_8">
          <num>R.8</num>
          <heading>Branchless banking agent network requirements</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_8__p_1">EMIs may appoint agents for cash-in and cash-out
              services subject to the following requirements:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_emi__reg_8__list_1">
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_8__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Each agent must be a person with a valid CNIC and a fixed business premises,
                  or a corporate entity registered in Pakistan;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_8__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The EMI shall perform due diligence on each agent before onboarding,
                  including verification of identity, business history, and financial standing;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_8__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Agent transactions shall be subject to the same per-transaction and aggregate
                  limits applicable to the customer's wallet tier;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_8__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>The EMI shall maintain a comprehensive agent management system with real-time
                  monitoring of agent activity, including flagging of unusual transaction
                  patterns;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_8__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>Agent float shall be maintained separately from the EMI's operational funds
                  and customer e-money float.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_emi__reg_10">
          <num>R.10</num>
          <heading>Safeguarding of customer funds</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_emi__reg_10__p_1">The EMI shall safeguard customer funds as follows:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_emi__reg_10__list_1">
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_10__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>All customer e-money funds (the float) shall be deposited in a trust account
                  maintained with one or more scheduled commercial banks licensed by SBP;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_10__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The trust account balance shall at all times equal or exceed
                  <num id="emi_10_safeguard">100%</num> of the total outstanding e-money
                  liabilities;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_10__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Trust account funds shall be invested only in liquid assets, including
                  Government of Pakistan Treasury Bills, balances with SBP, or balances with
                  scheduled commercial banks;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_10__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>The EMI shall not use customer float for its own operational expenses,
                  lending, or investment purposes beyond the permitted liquid asset classes;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_emi__reg_10__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>The trust account shall be audited quarterly by an external auditor, and the
                  audit report shall be submitted to SBP within 30 days of the quarter end.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <!-- PART V — FOREIGN EXCHANGE REGULATION ACT, 1947 (Act VII of 1947)   -->
      <!-- ================================================================== -->
      <part eId="part_fera">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1947 (Act VII of 1947)</heading>

        <section eId="part_fera__sec_4">
          <num>4</num>
          <heading>Authorized dealers</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_4__p_1">All foreign exchange transactions in Pakistan shall be
              conducted through authorized dealers, being banks or other entities licensed by the
              State Bank of Pakistan to deal in foreign exchange.</p>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_4__p_2">No person other than an authorized dealer shall:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_fera__sec_4__list_1">
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_4__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>buy, sell, borrow, or lend foreign exchange;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_4__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>make any payment to or for the credit of any person resident outside Pakistan;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_4__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receive any payment from or on behalf of any person resident outside Pakistan,
                  otherwise than through an authorized dealer or with the prior permission of
                  SBP.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_4__p_3">Exchange companies licensed by SBP may conduct limited
              foreign currency purchase and sale transactions for the purpose of facilitating
              inward remittances and currency exchange for travel purposes, subject to
              SBP-prescribed limits.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_fera__sec_5">
          <num>5</num>
          <heading>Capital account restrictions</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_5__p_1">The following capital account transactions require
              prior approval of SBP:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_fera__sec_5__list_1">
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_5__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Outward remittances by individuals exceeding
                  <num id="fera_5_individual">USD 10,000</num> (ten thousand United States
                  Dollars) per calendar year, including remittances for education, medical
                  treatment, gifts, and donations;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_5__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Direct investment abroad by Pakistani residents;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_5__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Acquisition or transfer of immovable property outside Pakistan;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_5__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Borrowing from non-residents or lending to non-residents;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_5__list_1__item_e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>Opening or maintaining bank accounts outside Pakistan, except as permitted by
                  SBP for specific purposes (e.g., diplomatic staff, students abroad).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_5__p_2">Inward remittances, including worker remittances and
              foreign direct investment, are generally permitted through authorized channels
              without prior SBP approval, subject to reporting requirements.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_fera__sec_8">
          <num>8</num>
          <heading>Export proceeds repatriation</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_8__p_1">Every exporter shall ensure that the full export
              proceeds are received in Pakistan through an authorized dealer within
              <num id="fera_8_repatriation">120</num> days from the date of shipment.</p>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_8__p_2">Where export proceeds are not received within the
              prescribed period, the authorized dealer shall report the overdue amount to SBP,
              and the exporter shall be liable to:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_fera__sec_8__list_1">
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_8__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a penalty not exceeding <num id="fera_8_penalty_pct">30%</num> of the
                  overdue amount, as may be imposed by SBP;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_8__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>suspension of further export facilities until the overdue amount is received
                  or written off with SBP approval;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_8__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>referral to the Federal Investigation Agency (FIA) for investigation if
                  foreign exchange regulation violations are suspected.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_8__p_3">SBP may grant extensions beyond 120 days in
              exceptional circumstances, including force majeure, contractual disputes, and
              country risk events, subject to documented application by the exporter through
              the authorized dealer.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="part_fera__sec_23">
          <num>23</num>
          <heading>Penalties for unauthorized foreign exchange dealing</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_23__p_1">Any person who contravenes any provision of this Act
              or any rule, regulation, direction, or order made thereunder shall be liable to:</p>
            <blockList eId="part_fera__sec_23__list_1">
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_23__list_1__item_a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A civil penalty not exceeding three times the amount involved in the
                  contravention, or <num id="fera_23_min_penalty">PKR 5,000,000</num> (five
                  million Pakistani Rupees), whichever is greater;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_23__list_1__item_b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>In the case of a continuing contravention, an additional penalty not exceeding
                  <num id="fera_23_daily_penalty">PKR 100,000</num> (one hundred thousand
                  Pakistani Rupees) for each day during which the contravention continues;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_23__list_1__item_c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Criminal prosecution under section 23-A, punishable with imprisonment for a
                  term which may extend to five years, or with fine, or with both, where the
                  contravention involves hawala/hundi transactions or systematic evasion of
                  exchange control regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="part_fera__sec_23__list_1__item_d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Confiscation of any foreign exchange, securities, or property involved in or
                  derived from the contravention.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p eId="part_fera__sec_23__p_2">The State Bank may, in addition to or in lieu of the
              penalties specified above, cancel or suspend the authorization of any authorized
              dealer or exchange company found to have contravened this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
