<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#mez">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/civil-corpus/0.1.0"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/civil-corpus"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="compilation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#secp"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="pk"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/civil-corpus/0.1.0/eng@"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/civil-corpus/eng@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="compilation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#secp"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/pk/act/civil-corpus/0.1.0/eng@.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/pk/act/civil-corpus/eng@.xml"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-01-01" name="compilation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#mez"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication name="MEZ Stack" showAs="MEZ Stack v0.4.44" date="2024-01-01" number="0.1.0"/>
      <references source="#mez">
        <TLCOrganization eId="secp" href="/ontology/organization/pk.secp" showAs="Securities and Exchange Commission of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="boi" href="/ontology/organization/pk.boi" showAs="Board of Investment, Government of Pakistan"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="mez" href="/ontology/organization/momentum.mez" showAs="Momentum EZ"/>
        <TLCOrganization eId="nationalassembly" href="/ontology/organization/pk.nationalassembly" showAs="National Assembly of Pakistan"/>
      </references>
    </meta>

    <preface>
      <p eId="preface_1">Pakistan civil and corporate law compilation for EZ Stack sovereign deployment.
        This document consolidates key provisions from the Companies Act 2017 (Act No. XL of 2017),
        the Contract Act 1872 (Act No. IX of 1872), the Special Economic Zones Act 2012
        (Act No. XII of 2012), and the Partnership Act 1932 (Act No. IX of 1932) as in force
        on 1 January 2024.</p>
      <p eId="preface_2">This compilation is provided for machine-readable regulatory analysis. It does not
        replace the official gazette text. All section numbers correspond to the published Acts.</p>
    </preface>

    <body>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART I — COMPANIES ACT 2017 (Act No. XL of 2017)                 -->
      <!-- Administered by: Securities and Exchange Commission of Pakistan   -->
      <!-- Gazette: Gazette of Pakistan, Extraordinary, Part I, 30 May 2017  -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->

      <part eId="part_companies">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Companies Act 2017 (Act No. XL of 2017)</heading>

        <section eId="ca2017_s16">
          <num>16</num>
          <heading>Incorporation of company</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s16__p1">(1) Any one or more persons associated for a lawful purpose may, by
              subscribing their names to a memorandum of association and complying with the requirements
              of this Act in respect of registration, form a private company.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s16__p2">(2) Any three or more persons so associated may form a public company.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s16__p3">(3) One person may form a single member company.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s16__p4">(4) An application for incorporation shall be filed with the registrar
              in the prescribed form and shall be accompanied by the following documents:
              (a) the memorandum of association; (b) the articles of association; (c) a declaration
              of compliance in the prescribed form; (d) the notice of the situation of the registered
              office; (e) a copy of the national identity card or passport of each subscriber;
              (f) particulars of the first directors and chief executive; and (g) such fee as may
              be prescribed.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s16__p5">(5) On registration, the registrar shall issue a certificate of
              incorporation in the prescribed form, and the company shall from the date of
              incorporation be a body corporate with perpetual succession and a common seal,
              capable of exercising all functions of an incorporated company under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s17">
          <num>17</num>
          <heading>Memorandum of association</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s17__p1">(1) The memorandum of every company shall state: (a) the name of the
              company with "Limited" or "(Private) Limited" as the last word; (b) the province in
              which the registered office of the company is to be situated; (c) the objects for
              which the company is proposed to be formed; (d) the liability of the members; and
              (e) the amount of authorized share capital with which the company is to be registered
              and the division thereof into shares of a fixed amount.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s17__p2">(2) The memorandum of a company limited by guarantee shall also state
              that each member undertakes to contribute to the assets of the company in the event
              of its being wound up while he is a member or within one year after he ceases to be
              a member, such amount as may be required, not exceeding a specified amount.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s17__p3">(3) In the case of a private company, the minimum paid-up capital
              shall be one hundred thousand rupees (PKR 100,000) or such other amount as may be
              prescribed by the Commission.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s17__p4">(4) In the case of a public company, the minimum paid-up capital
              shall be two hundred thousand rupees (PKR 200,000) or such other amount as the
              Commission may prescribe.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s18">
          <num>18</num>
          <heading>Articles of association</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s18__p1">(1) There shall be registered with the memorandum articles of
              association signed by each subscriber to the memorandum prescribing regulations for
              the company.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s18__p2">(2) Articles shall be in the form set out in Table A of the First
              Schedule or in a form as near thereto as circumstances admit, or in such other form
              as the Commission may approve.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s18__p3">(3) The articles shall be printed, divided into paragraphs numbered
              consecutively, and signed by each subscriber to the memorandum in the presence of at
              least one witness who shall attest the signature and shall likewise add his description
              and address.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s18__p4">(4) The articles may contain provisions for the management of the
              company's affairs including: (a) the transfer and transmission of shares; (b) the
              increase and reduction of share capital; (c) the convening and conduct of general
              meetings; (d) the appointment, powers, duties and remuneration of directors;
              (e) the payment of dividends; and (f) the keeping of accounts and audit.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s85">
          <num>85</num>
          <heading>Annual general meeting</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s85__p1">(1) Every company having a share capital shall in each year hold an
              annual general meeting in addition to any other meetings and shall specify the
              meeting as such in the notices calling it.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s85__p2">(2) The first annual general meeting of a company shall be held
              within a period of eighteen months from the date of its incorporation.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s85__p3">(3) Subsequent annual general meetings shall be held at intervals of
              not more than fifteen months, provided that the company shall hold an annual general
              meeting in each calendar year and not more than four months shall elapse between the
              date of one annual general meeting of the company and the last day of the following
              financial year.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s85__p4">(4) At every annual general meeting of a company, the following
              business shall be transacted: (a) consideration of the accounts, balance sheet and
              the reports of the directors and auditors; (b) the election or appointment of directors
              in place of those retiring; (c) the appointment of and the fixing of the remuneration
              of auditors; and (d) such other matters as may be prescribed or required under this Act.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s85__p5">(5) If default is made in holding an annual general meeting, the
              Commission may, on the application of any member of the company, call or direct the
              calling of an annual general meeting and give such ancillary or consequential
              directions as the Commission thinks expedient.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s119">
          <num>119</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of accounting records</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s119__p1">(1) Every company shall keep at its registered office proper books
              of account with respect to: (a) all sums of money received and expended by the company
              and the matters in respect of which the receipt and expenditure takes place;
              (b) all sales and purchases of goods by the company; (c) the assets and liabilities
              of the company; and (d) in the case of a company engaged in production, processing,
              manufacturing or mining activities, such particulars relating to utilization of
              material, labour and other items of overhead cost as may be prescribed.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s119__p2">(2) The books of account shall give a true and fair view of the
              state of affairs of the company and explain its transactions and shall be kept on
              accrual basis and according to the double entry system of accounting.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s119__p3">(3) Where a company has a branch office, whether in or outside
              Pakistan, the company shall ensure that proper books of account relating to the
              transactions effected at the branch office are kept at that office and proper
              summarized returns are sent to the registered office at intervals of not more
              than three months.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s119__p4">(4) The books of account of every company shall be preserved in
              good order for a period of not less than ten years from the date of the last entry
              therein, and where an investigation has been ordered, until the conclusion of the
              investigation.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s119__p5">(5) If any director or officer of the company fails to take
              reasonable steps to secure compliance with the requirements of this section or has
              by his own wilful act been the cause of any default, he shall be liable to a penalty
              which may extend to five hundred thousand rupees (PKR 500,000).</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s131">
          <num>131</num>
          <heading>Annual return</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s131__p1">(1) Every company shall prepare an annual return and file it with
              the registrar within thirty days from the date of each annual general meeting.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s131__p2">(2) The annual return shall be in the prescribed form and shall
              contain the following particulars as at the date of the annual general meeting:
              (a) the registered office; (b) a summary of share capital, debentures and charges;
              (c) the indebtedness of the company in respect of all charges which are required to
              be registered; (d) a list of members showing the shares held by each member and
              changes therein since the last return; (e) particulars of directors, chief executive,
              auditors and legal adviser and changes therein; and (f) such other particulars as
              may be prescribed.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s131__p3">(3) The annual return of a company having a share capital shall
              also include a certified copy of the audited financial statements as laid before the
              company in its annual general meeting.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s131__p4">(4) If a company fails to file its annual return within the period
              specified, the company and every officer who is in default shall be liable to a
              penalty of one hundred rupees (PKR 100) for each day of default, subject to a
              maximum of five hundred thousand rupees (PKR 500,000).</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s237">
          <num>237</num>
          <heading>Winding up by the Tribunal</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s237__p1">(1) A company may be wound up by the Tribunal if: (a) the company
              has by special resolution resolved that the company be wound up by the Tribunal;
              (b) the company has made a default in filing with the registrar its financial
              statements or annual returns for five consecutive financial years; (c) the company
              has acted against the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of Pakistan, the
              security of the state, friendly relations with foreign states, public order, decency
              or morality; (d) the Tribunal is of the opinion that it is just and equitable that
              the company should be wound up; (e) the company is unable to pay its debts;
              (f) the company has not commenced its business within a year from its incorporation
              and the Tribunal is of the opinion that the company was formed without bona fide
              intent to carry on business; or (g) the affairs of the company have been conducted
              in a manner oppressive to any member or in disregard of his interests as member.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s237__p2">(2) A company shall be deemed to be unable to pay its debts if:
              (a) a creditor by assignment or otherwise to whom the company is indebted in a sum
              exceeding the prescribed amount then due has served on the company a demand requiring
              the company to pay the sum so due and the company has for three weeks thereafter
              neglected to pay the sum; or (b) execution or other process issued on a decree or
              order of any court in favour of a creditor of the company is returned unsatisfied;
              or (c) it is proved to the satisfaction of the Tribunal that the company is unable
              to pay its debts, taking into account the contingent and prospective liabilities of
              the company.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s237__p3">(3) A petition for winding up may be presented by: (a) the company;
              (b) any creditor or creditors; (c) any contributory or contributories; (d) all or
              any of the parties specified in clauses (a), (b) and (c) together or separately;
              (e) the registrar; or (f) the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s460">
          <num>460</num>
          <heading>Company formation in Special Economic Zones</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s460__p1">(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Commission
              may, in consultation with the federal government, prescribe simplified procedures
              for the incorporation of companies within Special Economic Zones established under
              the Special Economic Zones Act, 2012.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s460__p2">(2) Such simplified procedures may include: (a) one-window
              registration combining company incorporation, tax registration and social security
              enrolment; (b) electronic filing and processing of all incorporation documents;
              (c) reduced timelines for issuance of certificates of incorporation; and
              (d) simplified forms and requirements for small and medium enterprises.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s460__p3">(3) The Commission may establish a dedicated desk or portal for
              companies being formed within Economic Zones and may coordinate with the zone
              authority for the purpose of registration and regulation.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s460__p4">(4) Companies incorporated under this section shall be subject
              to all provisions of this Act except to the extent modified by rules made under
              this section.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca2017_s461">
          <num>461</num>
          <heading>Reduced paid-up capital requirements for Economic Zone companies</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca2017_s461__p1">(1) Notwithstanding section 17, the Commission may prescribe
              reduced minimum paid-up capital requirements for companies formed and operating
              exclusively within a Special Economic Zone notified under the Special Economic
              Zones Act, 2012.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s461__p2">(2) Such reduced requirements shall not be less than: (a) fifty
              thousand rupees (PKR 50,000) for a private company; and (b) one hundred thousand
              rupees (PKR 100,000) for a public company.</p>
            <p eId="ca2017_s461__p3">(3) A company availing the reduced paid-up capital under this
              section shall not commence business outside the Economic Zone without first increasing
              its paid-up capital to the minimum prescribed under section 17 and obtaining fresh
              approval from the registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART II — CONTRACT ACT 1872 (Act No. IX of 1872)                  -->
      <!-- Adopted from pre-partition Indian legislation; remains in force    -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->

      <part eId="part_contract">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Contract Act 1872 (Act No. IX of 1872)</heading>

        <section eId="ca1872_s2">
          <num>2</num>
          <heading>Interpretation clause</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p1">When one person signifies to another his willingness to do or to
              abstain from doing anything, with a view to obtaining the assent of that other to such
              act or abstinence, he is said to make a <b>proposal</b>.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p2">When the person to whom the proposal is made signifies his assent
              thereto, the proposal is said to be accepted. A proposal, when accepted, becomes a
              <b>promise</b>.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p3">The person making the proposal is called the <b>promisor</b>, and
              the person accepting the proposal is called the <b>promisee</b>.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p4">When, at the desire of the promisor, the promisee or any other
              person has done or abstained from doing, or does or abstains from doing, or promises
              to do or to abstain from doing, something, such act or abstinence or promise is
              called a <b>consideration</b> for the promise.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p5">Every promise and every set of promises, forming the consideration
              for each other, is an <b>agreement</b>.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p6">An agreement enforceable by law is a <b>contract</b>.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p7">An agreement which is enforceable by law at the option of one or more
              of the parties thereto, but not at the option of the other or others, is a
              <b>voidable contract</b>.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s2__p8">An agreement not enforceable by law is said to be <b>void</b>.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s10">
          <num>10</num>
          <heading>What agreements are contracts</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s10__p1">All agreements are contracts if they are made by the free consent
              of parties competent to contract, for a lawful consideration and with a lawful object,
              and are not hereby expressly declared to be void.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s10__p2">Nothing herein contained shall affect any law in force in Pakistan
              and not hereby expressly repealed by which any contract is required to be made in
              writing or in the presence of witnesses, or any law relating to the registration of
              documents.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s11">
          <num>11</num>
          <heading>Who are competent to contract</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s11__p1">Every person is competent to contract who is of the age of majority
              according to the law to which he is subject, and who is of sound mind, and is not
              disqualified from contracting by any law to which he is subject.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s14">
          <num>14</num>
          <heading>Free consent defined</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s14__p1">Consent is said to be free when it is not caused by:
              (1) coercion, as defined in section 15; (2) undue influence, as defined in section 16;
              (3) fraud, as defined in section 17; (4) misrepresentation, as defined in section 18;
              or (5) mistake, subject to the provisions of sections 20, 21 and 22.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s14__p2">Consent is said to be so caused when it would not have been given
              but for the existence of such coercion, undue influence, fraud, misrepresentation
              or mistake.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s15">
          <num>15</num>
          <heading>Coercion defined</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s15__p1">Coercion is the committing, or threatening to commit, any act
              forbidden by the Pakistan Penal Code, or the unlawful detaining, or threatening to
              detain, any property, to the prejudice of any person whatever, with the intention of
              causing any person to enter into an agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s23">
          <num>23</num>
          <heading>What considerations and objects are lawful, and what not</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s23__p1">The consideration or object of an agreement is lawful,
              unless it is forbidden by law; or is of such a nature that, if permitted, it would
              defeat the provisions of any law; or is fraudulent; or involves or implies injury to
              the person or property of another; or the Court regards it as immoral, or opposed to
              public policy.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s23__p2">In each of these cases, the consideration or object of an agreement
              is said to be unlawful. Every agreement of which the object or consideration is
              unlawful is void.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Agreement without consideration void, unless in writing and registered</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s25__p1">An agreement made without consideration is void, unless: (1) it is
              expressed in writing and registered under the law for the time being in force for the
              registration of documents, and is made on account of natural love and affection
              between parties standing in a near relation to each other; or (2) it is a promise to
              compensate, wholly or in part, a person who has already voluntarily done something
              for the promisor, or something which the promisor was legally compellable to do; or
              (3) it is a promise, made in writing and signed by the person to be charged therewith,
              or by his agent generally or specially authorized in that behalf, to pay wholly or in
              part a debt of which the creditor might have enforced payment but for the law for the
              limitation of suits.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s73">
          <num>73</num>
          <heading>Compensation for loss or damage caused by breach of contract</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s73__p1">When a contract has been broken, the party who suffers by such
              breach is entitled to receive, from the party who has broken the contract, compensation
              for any loss or damage caused to him thereby, which naturally arose in the usual course
              of things from such breach, or which the parties knew, when they made the contract, to
              be likely to result from the breach of it.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s73__p2">Such compensation is not to be given for any remote and indirect
              loss or damage sustained by reason of the breach.</p>
            <p eId="ca1872_s73__p3">When an obligation resembling those created by contract has been
              incurred and has not been discharged, any person injured by the failure to discharge
              it is entitled to receive the same compensation from the party in default, as if such
              person had contracted to discharge it and had broken his contract.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s74">
          <num>74</num>
          <heading>Compensation for breach of contract where penalty stipulated for</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s74__p1">When a contract has been broken, if a sum is named in the contract
              as the amount to be paid in case of such breach, or if the contract contains any other
              stipulation by way of penalty, the party complaining of the breach is entitled, whether
              or not actual damage or loss is proved to have been caused thereby, to receive from the
              party who has broken the contract reasonable compensation not exceeding the amount so
              named or, as the case may be, the penalty stipulated for.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="ca1872_s75">
          <num>75</num>
          <heading>Party rightfully rescinding contract entitled to compensation</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="ca1872_s75__p1">A person who rightfully rescinds a contract is entitled to
              compensation for any damage which he has sustained through the non-fulfilment of the
              contract.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART III — SPECIAL ECONOMIC ZONES ACT 2012 (Act No. XII of 2012)  -->
      <!-- Administered by: Board of Investment, Government of Pakistan       -->
      <!-- Gazette: Gazette of Pakistan, Extraordinary, Part I, 2012          -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->

      <part eId="part_sez">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Special Economic Zones Act 2012 (Act No. XII of 2012)</heading>

        <section eId="sez2012_s2">
          <num>2</num>
          <heading>Definitions</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s2__p1">In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject
              or context:</p>
            <blockList eId="sez2012_s2__defs">
              <item eId="sez2012_s2__def_approval_board">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p><b>"Approval Board"</b> means the Board of Approval constituted under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sez2012_s2__def_developer">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p><b>"developer"</b> means a person who has been granted permission under this Act
                  to develop a Special Economic Zone;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sez2012_s2__def_sez">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p><b>"Special Economic Zone"</b> or <b>"Zone"</b> means a geographically delineated
                  area within the territory of Pakistan which is notified by the federal government
                  as a Special Economic Zone under section 3 of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sez2012_s2__def_enterprise">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p><b>"zone enterprise"</b> means any person who holds a valid licence granted
                  under section 14 to undertake manufacturing, processing, assembling, trading,
                  warehousing or the provision of services in a Special Economic Zone;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sez2012_s2__def_one_window">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p><b>"One Window Operation"</b> means the single-point facilitation mechanism
                  established under section 7 to provide all regulatory approvals, licences and
                  permits to zone developers and zone enterprises;</p>
              </item>
              <item eId="sez2012_s2__def_tariff_area">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p><b>"domestic tariff area"</b> means the whole of Pakistan except the Special
                  Economic Zones;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s3">
          <num>3</num>
          <heading>Establishment of Special Economic Zones</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s3__p1">(1) The federal government may, by notification in the official
              Gazette, establish one or more Special Economic Zones in any part of Pakistan.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s3__p2">(2) A provincial government or a private sector entity may propose
              the establishment of a Special Economic Zone in any area of the province, and the
              Approval Board shall consider and approve or reject such proposals on the basis of
              criteria prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s4">
          <num>4</num>
          <heading>Board of Approval</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s4__p1">(1) There shall be constituted a Board of Approval for the purposes
              of this Act, consisting of: (a) the Prime Minister or his nominee, who shall be
              chairperson; (b) the Chief Ministers of the provinces or their nominees; (c) the
              federal ministers for finance, commerce, industries and production, and planning;
              (d) the chairman of the Board of Investment; (e) two representatives of the private
              sector nominated by the federal government; and (f) such other members as the federal
              government may determine.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s4__p2">(2) The Board of Approval shall approve proposals for the
              establishment of Special Economic Zones, prescribe the terms and conditions for the
              grant of permits to developers, and review the performance of Special Economic Zones.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s4__p3">(3) The Board of Approval shall meet at least twice a year at
              such place and time as the chairperson may determine.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s7">
          <num>7</num>
          <heading>One Window Operation</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s7__p1">(1) The Board of Investment shall establish a One Window Operation
              at the federal level for the purpose of providing facilitation to zone developers and
              zone enterprises in obtaining all regulatory approvals, licences and permits required
              under any law.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s7__p2">(2) Each provincial government shall establish a provincial
              One Window Operation for facilitating zone developers and zone enterprises within the
              province.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s7__p3">(3) The One Window Operation shall have representatives of all
              relevant federal and provincial departments, and shall process applications within
              thirty days of receipt of a complete application.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s9">
          <num>9</num>
          <heading>Obligations of zone developer</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s9__p1">(1) The zone developer shall: (a) develop the infrastructure of
              the Special Economic Zone as specified in the development agreement, including roads,
              drainage, water supply, electricity, gas, telecommunications and waste disposal;
              (b) allocate space and provide developed plots or built-up space to zone enterprises;
              (c) ensure that the Special Economic Zone is demarcated and fenced or otherwise
              physically segregated from the domestic tariff area; (d) maintain common facilities
              and shared infrastructure; and (e) comply with all environmental laws and regulations
              applicable to the zone.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s9__p2">(2) The zone developer shall submit an annual report to the Board
              of Investment detailing the development progress, occupancy rates, investment levels,
              and employment generated within the zone.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s13">
          <num>13</num>
          <heading>Eligibility for zone enterprises</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s13__p1">(1) Any person, whether a company registered under the Companies
              Act or an association of persons, may apply to set up a zone enterprise, provided
              that: (a) the applicant proposes to carry on a business activity as approved for the
              zone; (b) the minimum investment is not less than the amount prescribed for the
              category of zone enterprise; and (c) the applicant has not been convicted of an
              offence involving fraud, tax evasion, or money laundering within the five years
              preceding the application.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s13__p2">(2) Preference shall be given to applications from enterprises
              proposing to undertake manufacturing, processing, assembling, or value-added services
              that generate employment and promote exports.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s13__p3">(3) A zone enterprise shall not undertake any activity prohibited
              by any law for the time being in force or any activity that the Board of Approval may
              specify as prohibited for a particular zone.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s14">
          <num>14</num>
          <heading>Licence to zone enterprises</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s14__p1">(1) Upon approval of an application under section 13, the zone
              authority shall issue a licence to the zone enterprise in the prescribed form.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s14__p2">(2) The licence shall specify: (a) the nature and scope of the
              business activities; (b) the area allocated within the zone; (c) the period of the
              licence and conditions for renewal; (d) the obligations of the enterprise regarding
              employment, investment and export targets; and (e) such other conditions as the zone
              authority may prescribe.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s23">
          <num>23</num>
          <heading>Import and export licensing simplification</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s23__p1">(1) Zone enterprises shall be exempt from import licensing
              requirements for goods imported into the zone for use in the manufacturing, processing,
              assembling or packaging of goods intended for export.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s23__p2">(2) Goods manufactured, processed, assembled or packaged within a
              zone may be exported without an export licence, provided that the zone enterprise
              maintains proper records of all imports and exports as prescribed by customs
              regulations.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s23__p3">(3) The movement of goods between a Special Economic Zone and the
              domestic tariff area shall be treated as import into or export from Pakistan and shall
              be subject to applicable customs duties and regulations, save as otherwise provided in
              this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s37">
          <num>37</num>
          <heading>Tax exemptions for zone enterprises</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s37__p1">(1) Subject to the conditions laid down in this Act and rules
              made thereunder, a zone enterprise that commences commercial production within the
              zone on or after the date of notification of the zone shall be entitled to exemption
              from income tax for a period of ten years from the date of commencement of commercial
              production.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s37__p2">(2) The ten-year exemption from income tax under sub-section (1)
              shall apply to income derived exclusively from operations within the Special Economic
              Zone.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s37__p3">(3) Zone developers shall be entitled to exemption from income tax
              for a period of ten years from the date of signing of the development agreement.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s37__p4">(4) The federal government may, by notification in the official
              Gazette, prescribe further tax incentives or modify the period of exemption for
              specific zones or categories of zone enterprises, having regard to the national
              interest and the objectives of this Act.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s37__p5">(5) A zone enterprise that relocates from the domestic tariff area
              to a Special Economic Zone shall not be eligible for the exemption under this section
              unless it makes new investment of the prescribed minimum amount.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s38">
          <num>38</num>
          <heading>Exemption from sales tax and federal excise duty</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s38__p1">(1) All goods imported into a Special Economic Zone for the
              purpose of a zone enterprise shall be exempt from sales tax and federal excise duty,
              subject to the conditions prescribed by rules.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s38__p2">(2) This exemption applies only where the goods are consumed or
              utilized within the zone or are incorporated into goods exported from the zone.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s39">
          <num>39</num>
          <heading>Customs duty exemption on capital goods</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s39__p1">(1) Capital goods, including plant, machinery and equipment,
              imported into a Special Economic Zone by a zone developer or zone enterprise for the
              development, operation or maintenance of the zone or for use in manufacturing,
              processing, assembling or other authorized activities within the zone shall be exempt
              from customs duties.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s39__p2">(2) The exemption under sub-section (1) shall be subject to the
              following conditions: (a) the capital goods shall be used exclusively within the zone;
              (b) the zone developer or zone enterprise shall furnish an undertaking to customs
              authorities that the goods will not be sold or transferred to the domestic tariff area
              without payment of applicable duties; (c) the zone developer or zone enterprise shall
              maintain a register of all duty-free imports and make it available for inspection by
              customs officers; and (d) any transfer of duty-exempt capital goods to the domestic
              tariff area shall be subject to payment of customs duty calculated on the depreciated
              value of the goods at the rates applicable at the time of such transfer.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s39__p3">(3) Raw materials and intermediary goods imported for use in the
              manufacturing or processing of goods for export shall be exempt from customs duties
              subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="sez2012_s40">
          <num>40</num>
          <heading>Labour laws</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="sez2012_s40__p1">(1) All labour laws in force in Pakistan shall apply to Special
              Economic Zones.</p>
            <p eId="sez2012_s40__p2">(2) Notwithstanding sub-section (1), the federal government may,
              by notification in the official Gazette and in consultation with the provinces,
              provide for simplified labour compliance procedures within zones, provided that the
              core labour standards recognized under international conventions ratified by Pakistan
              shall not be derogated.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART IV — PARTNERSHIP ACT 1932 (Act No. IX of 1932)               -->
      <!-- Inherited pre-partition legislation; governs general partnerships  -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->

      <part eId="part_partnership">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Partnership Act 1932 (Act No. IX of 1932)</heading>

        <section eId="pa1932_s4">
          <num>4</num>
          <heading>Definition of partnership</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="pa1932_s4__p1">"Partnership" is the relation between persons who have agreed to
              share the profits of a business carried on by all or any of them acting for all.</p>
            <p eId="pa1932_s4__p2">Persons who have entered into partnership with one another are
              called individually "partners" and collectively "a firm," and the name under which
              their business is carried on is called the "firm name."</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="pa1932_s5">
          <num>5</num>
          <heading>Relation of partnership arising from contract</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="pa1932_s5__p1">The relation of partnership arises from contract and not from
              status; and, in particular, the members of a Hindu undivided family carrying on a
              family business as such, or a Burmese Buddhist husband and wife carrying on business
              as such, are not partners in such business.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="pa1932_s25">
          <num>25</num>
          <heading>Every partner is agent of the firm</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="pa1932_s25__p1">Subject to the provisions of this Act, every partner is the agent
              of the firm for the purposes of the business of the firm. The act of every partner
              which is done to carry on, in the usual way, business of the kind carried on by the
              firm, binds the firm, unless the partner so acting has in fact no authority to act for
              the firm in the particular matter, and the person with whom he is dealing knows that
              he has no such authority, or does not know or believe him to be a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="pa1932_s69">
          <num>69</num>
          <heading>Registration of firms</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="pa1932_s69__p1">(1) The registration of a firm may be effected at any time by
              filing with the Registrar of Firms an application stating: (a) the firm name;
              (b) the place or principal place of business of the firm; (c) the names of any other
              places where the firm carries on business; (d) the date when each partner joined the
              firm; (e) the names in full and permanent addresses of the partners; and (f) the
              duration of the firm.</p>
            <p eId="pa1932_s69__p2">(2) The application shall be signed by all the partners, or by
              their agents specially authorized in this behalf.</p>
            <p eId="pa1932_s69__p3">(3) No suit to enforce a right arising from a contract shall be
              instituted in any court by or on behalf of any person suing as a partner in a firm
              against the firm or against any person alleged to be or to have been a partner in the
              firm unless the firm is registered and the person suing is or has been shown in the
              Register of Firms as a partner in the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
      <!-- PART V — CROSS-CUTTING PROVISIONS AND EZ STACK ANNOTATIONS        -->
      <!-- Machine-readable compliance notes for the pack pipeline           -->
      <!-- ================================================================ -->

      <part eId="part_annotations">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Cross-Cutting Compliance Annotations</heading>

        <section eId="annot_incorporation">
          <num>A1</num>
          <heading>Company incorporation requirements summary</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="annot_incorporation__p1">For EZ Stack zone deployments in Pakistan, the minimum
              incorporation requirements are: (a) private company: at least one subscriber, minimum
              paid-up capital PKR 100,000 (or PKR 50,000 within a notified SEZ per section 461
              Companies Act 2017); (b) public company: at least three subscribers, minimum paid-up
              capital PKR 200,000 (or PKR 100,000 within a notified SEZ); (c) single member company:
              one subscriber, minimum paid-up capital PKR 100,000.</p>
            <p eId="annot_incorporation__p2">Documents required: memorandum of association, articles
              of association, declaration of compliance, registered office notice, NIC/passport copies
              of subscribers, and particulars of first directors and chief executive (section 16
              Companies Act 2017).</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="annot_compliance_calendar">
          <num>A2</num>
          <heading>Annual compliance calendar obligations</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="annot_compliance_calendar__p1">Every registered company must: (a) hold an AGM
              within 18 months of incorporation and annually thereafter, with not more than 15 months
              between consecutive AGMs (section 85 Companies Act 2017); (b) file an annual return
              with the registrar within 30 days of the AGM (section 131); (c) maintain books of
              account on accrual basis for a minimum of 10 years (section 119).</p>
            <p eId="annot_compliance_calendar__p2">Penalties for non-compliance: late annual return
              filing attracts PKR 100 per day of default, maximum PKR 500,000. Failure to maintain
              accounting records: director/officer penalty up to PKR 500,000.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="annot_sez_benefits">
          <num>A3</num>
          <heading>SEZ fiscal incentive summary</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="annot_sez_benefits__p1">Zone enterprises commencing commercial production within
              a notified SEZ are entitled to: (a) ten-year income tax exemption from date of
              commercial production commencement (section 37 SEZ Act 2012); (b) exemption from sales
              tax and federal excise on goods imported for zone use (section 38); (c) customs duty
              exemption on capital goods including plant, machinery and equipment (section 39);
              (d) import licensing waiver for goods used in export manufacturing (section 23);
              (e) simplified one-window registration (section 7, read with section 460 Companies
              Act 2017).</p>
            <p eId="annot_sez_benefits__p2">Zone developers are separately entitled to a ten-year
              income tax exemption from the date of signing the development agreement (section 37(3)
              SEZ Act 2012).</p>
            <p eId="annot_sez_benefits__p3">Restriction: enterprises relocating from the domestic
              tariff area to an SEZ must make new investment of the prescribed minimum to qualify
              for the ten-year exemption (section 37(5)).</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="annot_contract_validity">
          <num>A4</num>
          <heading>Contract validity requirements for EZ transactions</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="annot_contract_validity__p1">All agreements executed within or in connection with
              an EZ-governed zone must satisfy the requirements of the Contract Act 1872: (a) free
              consent of parties competent to contract (sections 10, 11, 14); (b) lawful
              consideration and lawful object (section 23); (c) agreement not declared void under
              the Act (section 10). Agreements that fail these conditions are void ab initio and
              unenforceable.</p>
            <p eId="annot_contract_validity__p2">For digital contracts executed through EZ Stack
              platform: electronic signatures are recognized under the Electronic Transactions
              Ordinance 2002 (Ordinance No. LI of 2002), provided that the signatory has consented
              and the method of signature creation is reliable and linked to the signatory.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="annot_winding_up">
          <num>A5</num>
          <heading>Company dissolution and winding-up triggers</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="annot_winding_up__p1">Grounds for compulsory winding up by the Tribunal include:
              (a) special resolution for winding up; (b) five consecutive years of failure to file
              financial statements or annual returns; (c) acts against sovereignty, public order or
              morality; (d) just and equitable ground; (e) inability to pay debts; (f) failure to
              commence business within one year; (g) oppressive or prejudicial conduct of affairs
              (section 237 Companies Act 2017).</p>
            <p eId="annot_winding_up__p2">A company is deemed unable to pay its debts if a creditor's
              statutory demand exceeding the prescribed amount remains unsatisfied for three weeks,
              or execution is returned unsatisfied, or the Tribunal is otherwise satisfied of
              insolvency including contingent and prospective liabilities.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

        <section eId="annot_partnership">
          <num>A6</num>
          <heading>Partnership registration implications</heading>
          <content>
            <p eId="annot_partnership__p1">Under section 69 of the Partnership Act 1932, an
              unregistered firm cannot institute a suit to enforce a contractual right. EZ Stack zone
              deployments should ensure that partnership entities operating within the zone are
              registered with the Registrar of Firms. Every partner acts as agent of the firm
              (section 25) and can bind the firm in the usual course of business.</p>
          </content>
        </section>

      </part>

    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
